Bob Stevens Papers
Bob Stevens Papers
1966-1970.
Stevens, Bob, 1923-1994.
2.83 linear ft.
135 original editorial cartoons, printed material and an engraving plate (with a copy of the cartoon).
2651168
Biographical History
Robert Merrill Stevens (1923-1994), commonly known as Bob Stevens, was an American cartoonist and illustrator.
Bob Stevens, born in Iowa in 1923, became interested in drawing at age seven and graduated from Syracuse University with a B.A. Stevens joined the Air Force, as a pilot, and served for 22 years before retiring in 1964. During his military career, Stevens contributed cartoons to the Army Times and Stars and Stripes.
His comic strip, Clementine, distributed by the Lew Little Syndicate debuted in July 1965. He joined Copley Newspapers (publishers of the San Diego Union Tribune) as an editorial cartoonist and his cartoons appeared in 300 papers. In 1972 he left Copley to pursue freelance work. Stevens, influenced by his Air Force career, was also known for his aviation cartoons which appeared in Private Pilot magazine in the 1970s and 1980s and in Professional Pilot. His published books include: There I Was, Flat On My Back (1968) and More There I Was (1974). He also served as the cartoon editor for Trailer Life Publications.
Stevens was a member of the National Cartoonists Society. He received five Freedoms Foundation awards and was nominated for the Pulitzer Prize.
Bob Stevens died in 1994.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bob Stevens Papers (1966-1970) contain primarily original editorial cartoons.
The Cartoons series (1966-1970) is comprised of 135 original editorial cartoons drawn by Stevens for syndication through Copley Newspapers. The cartoons typically bear two dates: one on the front indicating the day on which the cartoon was to appear and a stamped date on the back listing the day the engraver received the cartoon prior to publication. For the purpose of this finding aid, the date on the front of the cartoon has been used where possible. Note that cartoons dating to 1970 are stamped with an engraving date of "1960".
The cartoons were drawn primarily with ink and crayon on illustration board with dot screening. Many pieces from 1969 and 1970 (see Oversize Box 3) were created on Grafix paper. Captions and dates appear in pencil. Dimensions vary but the majority of the cartoons measure 11" x 14".
Printed material contains one copy of the Copley Press from Winter 1969.
The Engraving plate is of Stevens' cartoon about the death of Walt Disney (1966). It shows Mickey Mouse in a spotlight with a tear running down his cheek. A 8"x10" copy of the cartoon is included.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons are arranged in chronological order.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Stevens, Bob, 1923-1994.; Copley Press, inc.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; College students -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Demonstrations -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Peace -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics--1965-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; China -- Politics and government -- 1949-1976 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1945-1991 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1969-1974 --Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Printing plates.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Bob Stevens, 1967-1970.
Inventory
- Cartoons, 11" x 14"; Click here for a detailed inventory.; See below for an index to the cartoons.
  - 1966 Jan - Mar (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - 1966 Apr - Jun (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - 1966 Jul - Aug (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - 1966 Sep - Oct (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - 1966 Nov - Dec (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - 1967 Jan - Mar (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
  - 1967 Apr - May, 1967 Jul, 1967 Sep, 1967 Nov - Dec (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
  - 1968 Jan, 1968 Mar - Apr (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
  - 1968 May - Aug (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
  - 1968 Sep, 1968 Nov - Dec (Oversize 2, Folder 5)
  - 1969 Jan - Apr (Oversize 2, Folder 6)
  - 1969 May - Aug (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
  - 1970 Jan - Mar (Oversize 3, Folder 2)
  - 1970 Apr - May (Oversize 3, Folder 3)
  - 1970 Jun - Jul (Oversize 3, Folder 4)
  - 1970 Aug - Nov (Oversize 3, Folder 5)
- Printed material
  - Copley Press, Winter 1969; contains cartoon by Stevens and short blurb about Stevens (Oversize 3)
- Engraving plate, 4 3/4" x 6 1/2" x 1/16"
  - Walt Disney's death with copy of the cartoon, 1966 Dec (Oversize 3)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Africa B1F1
anarchy B2F4
anti-missile systems B2F2 B3F1 B3F5
Argentina B1F2
armed forces B1F4 B3F5
Asia B1F4-B1F5 B2F5
auto industry B3F5
Berlin Wall B1F3
birth control B2F6
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B1F3 B1F5 B2F2 B3F1 B3F5
Britain B1F1 B1F3
Bulgaria B2F4
Cambodia B2F3 B3F3-B3F4
Castro, Fidel B1F1 B1F5
Chile B3F5
China B1F1-B1F3 B1F5-B2F1 B2F3 B3F3
college students B2F1 B3F2 B3F4-B3F5
common market B1F5 B2F2
communism B1F5 B3F2 B3F5
Congress B2F1 B2F3-B2F4 B3F4-B3F5
crime B2F2-B2F3 B3F1
Cuba B1F1 B1F5
Czechoslovakia B2F4-B2F5 B3F1
de Gaulle, Charles B1F1-B1F5 B2F2-B2F3 B2F5-B2F6
demonstrations B2F2 B3F3 B3F5
Dirksen, Everett B1F3
draft B2F2
drug use B1F2 B2F1-B2F2 B3F2
education B3F2
Eisenhower, Dwight B2F4 B2F6
elections B1F4-B1F5
Erhard, Ludwig B1F5
Europe B2F6-B3F1
Food and Drug Administration B1F2
food prices B1F2
foreign aid B1F3 B2F4
Formosa B1F5
France B3F2
Fulbright, J. William B1F2 B3F3
Germany B1F5 B2F5 B3F1
gold reserve B2F2-B2F3
government spending B2F3
Great Society B2F1-B2F2
Gromyko, Andrei B1F4
hate B2F3
hijackings B3F2-B3F3
Hitler, Adolph B2F4
Ho Chi Minh B1F3
Humphrey, Hubert B2F3 B2F5
Hungary B2F4
Illia, Arturo Umberto B1F2
India B1F1
Indonesia B1F1
inflation B1F4 B2F4 B3F3
isolationism B3F2
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F2 B1F5-B2F4 B2F6
Jordan B3F5
Kennedy, Robert F. B2F3
Kent State University B3F5
Kosygin, Alexey B1F2 B1F3 B1F5
Ky, Nguyen Cao B1F2-B1F3
Latin America B2F6
liberty B3F4
Libya B3F2
LSD B1F2 B2F1
Malaysia B1F3 B1F5
May Day B2F2
McCarthy, Eugene B2F3
McNamara, Robert B1F4 B2F1-B2F2
Meir, Golda B3F5
Middle East B2F2 B2F6 B3F4
military industrial complex B3F1
Nasser, Gamal Abdel B2F4 B3F4-B3F5
nationalism B1F5
NATO B1F1-B1F2 B2F4
nature B3F4
Nixon, Richard M. B2F4 B2F6 B3F3 B3F5
North Korea B2F6
nuclear weapons B2F6
Pakistan B1F1
peace B1F1 B1F3-B1F4 B2F3-B2F6 B3F5
Peru B2F6
Philippines B1F5
Poland B3F1
pollution B3F1 B3F3 B3F5
Poor People's Campaign B2F4
prisoners of war B3F3
protesters B2F2 B3F2 B3F5
Rhodesia B1F1-B1F2
riots B2F2-B2F3
Romania B3F1
Russia B1F1-B1F3 B2F2-B2F3
Sihanouk, Norodom B2F3 B3F3
Smith, Ian B1F1
smut B2F1
South America B3F5
Soviet Union B1F1 B1F3 B2F3-B2F5 B3F1 B3F4-B3F5
space exploration B1F1 B3F4
strikes B1F2
Suez Canal B3F4
Sukarno B1F1 B1F3
Supreme Court B2F1
Syria B3F5
taxes B2F1 B2F3-B2F4 B2F6 B3F3
terrorism B3F4-B3F5
Thailand B1F5
Thant, U. B2F1
U.S. Postal Service B2F4
United Auto Workers B3F5
United Nations B1F4 B3F5
USS Pueblo B2F3 B2F6
Vietnam War B1F1-B2F3 B2F5-B3F4
voting B3F4
Warren, Earl B3F1
welfare B2F2 B3F3 B3F5
Wilson, Harold B1F1 B1F3 B1F5 B2F2
World War II B2F2 B3F3
Zedong, Mao B1F1-B1F2 B1F4-B1F5